<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>A Technology Journal</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/</link><description>Recent content on A Technology Journal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:50:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.danvalencia.dev/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Talks</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/talks/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:50:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/talks/</guid><description>Diseño de un sistema de gestión de archivos escalable y resiliente Talk in spanish given at Software Guru Virtual 2020
Download presentation</description></item><item><title>Instant Pot Lentil Soup</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/recipes/lentil_soup/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 17:50:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/recipes/lentil_soup/</guid><description>Ingredients 2 tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil 1 medium yellow onion — small diced 4 medium carrots 3 stalks celery 4 springs fresh thyme 1 teaspoon kosher salt 3&amp;frasl;4 teaspoon smoked paprika 1&amp;frasl;2 teaspoon black pepper 2 cups red lentils 4 cloves garlic — minced (about 4 teaspoons) 1 can fire-roasted diced tomatoes — (15 ounces) 1 can fire-roasted crushed tomatoes — (15 ounces) 6 cups broth (veggie, beef or chicken will work well) Preparation Drizzle the oil into the Instant Pot.</description></item><item><title>Automating my website build with Github Actions</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/automating_my_website_build_with_github_actions/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 13:55:20 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/automating_my_website_build_with_github_actions/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve had this website for 6 years now. Like any piece of software, a website needs constant care and things end up breaking if you abandon it. In this post I&amp;rsquo;ll discuss how I revamped my site and automated my site&amp;rsquo;s build using Github Actions.
The original setup I built this website from the beginning with Hugo, which is a very popular static site generator written in Go. I&amp;rsquo;ve been very happy with it: it&amp;rsquo;s very easy to setup, it&amp;rsquo;s fast, and it uses Markdown which is my favorite language for writing.</description></item><item><title>Implementing SSO with hybris</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/implementing_sso_with_hybris/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2015 10:50:03 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/implementing_sso_with_hybris/</guid><description>This is the story of how I implemented Single Sign-On (SSO) functionality with hybris
The Requirements When the client requested us to implement SSO functionality with hybris there didn&amp;rsquo;t provide much details besides the Identity Provider (IdP) of choice, which was Okta. The client had already implemented SSO for other applications (namely Widen, a cloud base DAM), and given that there was zero experience doing this with hybris we were somehow convinced that it was an easy feature to implement (mistake #1).</description></item><item><title>Hands (Part I)</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/hands_part_1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2013 10:56:50 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/hands_part_1/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m currently helping my friend Dave Gertler to build his Burning Man art installation which is called Hands. Specifically I&amp;rsquo;ll be focusing on the electronics, which is a fairly big chunk of work. In this post I&amp;rsquo;ll introduce you to the project and show you some of the work we&amp;rsquo;ve been doing to make this a reality.
Intro The installation consists of 2 hands with the palms facing upwards. The hands will be made out of CDX plywood and the piece is designed to be assembled as a huge 3D jigsaw puzzle.</description></item><item><title>Closures and Scoping in Javascript</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/closures_and_scoping_in_javascript/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2013 10:53:43 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/closures_and_scoping_in_javascript/</guid><description>Per Wikipedia, a Closure is:
&amp;hellip; a function or reference to a function together with a referencing environment—a table storing a reference to each of the non-local variables (also called free variables) of that function.
I want you to pay special attention to the last part of that definition: together with a referencing environment, containing references to each of the non-local variables of that function. This is easier explained with a little code:</description></item><item><title>A Performance Testing Methodology</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/a_performance_testing_methodology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2012 10:50:03 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/a_performance_testing_methodology/</guid><description>The primary goal of any web site performance testing and capacity planning activity is to know how many users can our system handle under acceptable response times given certain hardware specifications. We can get this information by graphing a concurrency vs response time graph.
A typical graph looks like this:
Note how the curve grows exponentially. Depending on the nature of the website (or web pages) under test you might have different acceptable response times.</description></item><item><title>Notes On Continuous Delivery</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/notes_on_continuous_delivery/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 10:27:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/articles/notes_on_continuous_delivery/</guid><description>Only Build Your Binaries Once Reduce the risk of introducing difference on each build. Takes time to compile code (specially in large systems) Deploy the Same Way to Every Environment Once you reach Production you are confident that your deployments work. Smoke-Test your Deployments After deploying, immediately make sure that the most basic functionality works as expected. Deploy into a copy of Production Make your environments a similar to production as pipeline.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/about/resume-slim/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/about/resume-slim/</guid><description>Daniel Valencia Backhoff, Software Engineer Professional Summary I have over 10 years of experience as a software engineer and technical lead across a diverse set of projects that span from greenfield development to big complex integration projects with startups and enterprises in the fields of eCommerce, media, real estate, and AEC.
I am a generalist that enjoys a good challenge. My strength lies on my breadth of experience: backend development, UI, mobile app development, infrastructure engineering, QA, performance/load testing, and people management.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/about/resume/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/about/resume/</guid><description>Click to download a PDF version of my resume
Daniel Valencia Backhoff, Software Engineer Professional Summary I have over 15 years of experience as a software engineer and technical leader across a diverse set of projects that span from greenfield development to complex integration projects with startups and enterprises in the fields of retail, media, real estate, and AEC.
I am a generalist that enjoys a good challenge. My strength lies on my breadth of experience: backend development, UI, mobile app development, infrastructure engineering, QA, performance/load testing, and people management.</description></item><item><title>About me</title><link>https://www.danvalencia.dev/about/me/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.danvalencia.dev/about/me/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m an experienced software developer from Ensenada, México, currently working as a Director of Engineering at HELIX RE, in San Francisco, California.
I&amp;rsquo;d say curiosity is one of my biggest strengths, and that has helped me get involved in the entire software development stack: from frontend, backend, and mobile app development to infrastructure engineering, QA, and performance testing. I&amp;rsquo;m a technologist at heart who loves solving hard problems; I&amp;rsquo;m a generalist who believes in using the right tool for the job.</description></item></channel></rss>